<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xslt/atom.xslt" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="/assets/css/atom.css" ?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<id>http://localhost:4000/</id>
	<title>Konstantin Nomerotski - Portfolio</title>
	<updated>2024-12-06T18:40:43+00:00</updated>

	<subtitle>» Showcasing my portfolio in Chemistry, Computing, and Data Science «</subtitle>

	
		
		<author>
			
				<name>Konstantin Nomerotski</name>
			
			
			
		</author>
	

	<link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />

	<generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator>

	
		<entry>
			<id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/an-investigation-on-wine/</id>
			<title>An investigation on wine</title>
			<link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/an-investigation-on-wine/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An investigation on wine" />
			<updated>2024-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Konstantin N</name>
					
					
						<email>kon50@hotmail.co.uk</email>
					
					
						<uri>http://k-nom.com</uri>
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>Can we use machine learning for classifying wine? How can we tell if a wine is good or bad?</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/an-investigation-on-wine/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-dataset&quot;&gt;The Dataset&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this project, I used the “wine-dataset” sourced from the UCI machine learning repository. The dataset contains 6497 samples, each representing a different wine. The dataset has 12 features, including physiochemical properties such as fixed acidity, volatile acidity, citric acid, residual sugar, chlorides, free sulfur dioxide, total sulfur dioxide, density, pH, sulphates, and alcohol content. Additionally, the dataset provides a quality score ranging from 0 to 9, with higher scores indicating better quality, although the lowest score given is 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-objective&quot;&gt;The Objective&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project aimed to address two key questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Can we classify wines as red or white based on their chemical properties?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Can we predict the “goodness” of wines?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How do we make better wines?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Binary logistic regression was chosen to classify the wines. To explore the latter question, I used Bayesian inference to investigate the relationship between the physiochemical properties and the probability of a wine being classified as “good,” based on the quality score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-results&quot;&gt;The Results!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A binary logistic regression (BLR) model was constructed to predict wine type using six variables. The model achieved 97.3% accuracy, with precision, recall, and F1 scores all above 98%. Five-fold cross-validation showed consistent performance across different subsets of the data.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bayesian inference was used to estimate the probability of a wine being classified as “good” based on a quality score threshold of six. The average probability (theta) was found to be 63%, with a narrow posterior distribution indicating high confidence in the estimate.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The relationship between citric acid concentration and the probability of a wine being “good” was investigated using Bayesian inference. The results showed that wines with citric acid levels between 0.29 and 0.34 g.dm-3 had the highest probability of being rated as “good”. This suggests that winemakers could aim for this citric acid range to increase the likelihood of producing high-quality wines.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;techincal-details&quot;&gt;Techincal details&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&quot;data-exploration-cleaning-and-preprocessing&quot;&gt;Data exploration, cleaning and preprocessing&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before diving into modelling, I preprocessed the data to ensure its quality and suitability for analysis. This involved handling missing values (if any), addressing potential outliers, and scaling numerical features to a standard range. Additionally, I encoded the wine type (red or white) as a binary variable for use in logistic regression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;logistic-regression&quot;&gt;Logistic regression&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logistic regression is a suitable algorithm for binary classification tasks, making it a good choice for predicting wine type. Using Recursive Feature Elimination (RFE) with logistic regression, I selected six features for the model: chlorides, residual sugar, fixed acidity, volatile acidity, pH, and sulphates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/conf_mat_wine.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The model achieved an impressive accuracy of 97.3% on the test data, demonstrating its effectiveness in distinguishing between red and white wines. Further evaluation using precision, recall, and F1-score all yielded values above 98%, indicating a high level of confidence in the model’s predictions. The confusion matrix visually confirmed the model’s performance, showing a low number of misclassifications. Finally, the ROC curve, with an area under the curve (AUC) of 0.97, reinforces the model’s excellent discriminatory ability. Furthermore, the model showed to be robust with a k-fold cross-val score of 0.97 using 5 folds, suggesting little variation in accuracy for new sets of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While logistic regression is a powerful tool, it has some limitations. It assumes a linear relationship between the independent variables and the logit of the dependent variable, which may not always hold true. Additionally, it requires careful handling of multicollinearity, which I addressed through feature selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;bayesian-inference---good-or-bad-wine&quot;&gt;Bayesian inference - Good or Bad wine?&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To gain a deeper understanding of wine quality, I turned to Bayesian inference. This approach allows us to incorporate prior knowledge and update our beliefs about the probability of a wine being “good” as we observe more data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/quality_count_wine.png&quot; style=&quot;width:80%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this analysis, I defined a wine as “good” if its quality score was 6 or higher. I used a beta distribution as the prior, reflecting the initial belief that a slightly higher proportion of wines would be classified as “good”. The binomial likelihood function was used to update the prior based on the observed data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/bay_inf_wine.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bayesian analysis resulted in an average theta (θ) value of 0.632, representing the overall probability of a wine being “good” in the dataset. The narrow posterior width of 0.006 indicates a high level of certainty in this estimate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&quot;a-closer-look-at-citric-acid&quot;&gt;A closer look at citric acid&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To investigate the influence of citric acid on wine quality, I divided the citric acid values into eight approximately equally populated bins. I then performed Bayesian inference for each bin, calculating the average theta and posterior width.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;../../images/Citric_acid_wine.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results revealed an interesting trend: wines with citric acid levels between 0.29 and 0.34 g.dm-3 had the highest probability of being classified as “good”. This suggests a “sweet spot” for citric acid content, where it positively contributes to perceived quality.
This insight can be valuable for winemakers, allowing them to optimise citric acid levels to potentially enhance the quality of their wines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;widget-grid&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;widget&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kon-218/wine_investigation&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.githubassets.com/images/modules/logos_page/GitHub-Mark.png&quot; alt=&quot;GitHub&quot; style=&quot;width:40px; height:40px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;See the Code! (As a notebook)&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;t60&quot;&gt;Other Projects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;side-nav&quot;&gt;

  

    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/portfolio/an-investigation-on-wine/&quot;&gt;Data Science &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;An investigation on wine&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/portfolio/this-website/&quot;&gt;Web development &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;This Website&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/portfolio/rep-sampling-for-nea/&quot;&gt;Data Science &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;Representative Samping for the Nuclear Ensemble Approach&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/portfolio/cloud-paradigm-atlas-data-processing/&quot;&gt;Cloud paradigms &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;Improving scalability using cloud paradigms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/portfolio/biscuit-dunking-analysis/&quot;&gt;Data Science &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;Biscuit Dunking Data Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/portfolio/atmospec-data-visualization-module/&quot;&gt;Data Visualization &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;Atmospec Visualization Module&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/portfolio/accelerating-python-code/&quot;&gt;Increasing Efficiency &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;Accelerating Python code&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li class=&quot;text-right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/archive/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More ›&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;


  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>

			
				<category term="projects" />
			
			
				<category term="Data Science" />
			
				<category term="Wine" />
			
				<category term="Bayesian inference" />
			
				<category term="Machine Learning" />
			
				<category term="Data visualization" />
			
				<category term="Python" />
			
				<category term="Wine Classification" />
			
				<category term="Regression" />
			

			<published>2024-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>http://localhost:4000/blog/identifying-functional-groups</id>
			<title>Identifying molecular functional groups</title>
			<link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/identifying-functional-groups" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Identifying molecular functional groups" />
			<updated>2024-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Konstantin N</name>
					
					
						<email>kon50@hotmail.co.uk</email>
					
					
						<uri>http://k-nom.com</uri>
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>An algorithm for FG analysis</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/identifying-functional-groups">&lt;h3 id=&quot;coming-soon&quot;&gt;Coming soon!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 class=&quot;t60&quot;&gt;Other Blog posts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;side-nav&quot;&gt;

  

    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/identifying-functional-groups&quot;&gt;Computational Chemistry &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;Identifying molecular functional groups&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/nuclear-ensemble-approach&quot;&gt;Photochemistry &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;The Nuclear Ensemble Approach&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/what-is-atmospec&quot;&gt;Atmospheric Chemistry &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;AtmoSpec: A Revolutionary Tool for Atmospheric Chemists&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/predicting-solubility&quot;&gt;Computational Chemistry &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;Predicting molecular properties: Solubility&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li class=&quot;text-right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/archive/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More ›&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;


  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>

			
				<category term="blog" />
			
			
				<category term="Structure" />
			
				<category term="Computational Chemistry" />
			
				<category term="RDKit" />
			
				<category term="Machine Learning" />
			
				<category term="Molecular Representations" />
			
				<category term="Python" />
			

			<published>2024-11-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>http://localhost:4000/blog/nuclear-ensemble-approach</id>
			<title>The Nuclear Ensemble Approach</title>
			<link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/nuclear-ensemble-approach" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Nuclear Ensemble Approach" />
			<updated>2024-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Konstantin N</name>
					
					
						<email>kon50@hotmail.co.uk</email>
					
					
						<uri>http://k-nom.com</uri>
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>A method for the calculation of photoabsorption cross-sections</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/nuclear-ensemble-approach">&lt;p&gt;The Atmosphere is an extremely complex environment with many reactions occuring at the same time, some of those reactions are spontaneous on exposure to light. For example, smog is a result of light induced photochemical reactions between nitrous oxides (NOx) and other volatile organic compounds (VOCs). Traditionally, the reactive properties of such volatile gasses are measured empirically, however this is extremely difficult due to their unstable nature. So how do scientists predict the interaction of molecules with light?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent advances in Computational Chemistry have enabled the insilico calculation of photochemical properties, using Quantum Chemistry methods to predict quantities such as the molecular photoabsorption cross-section. One fascinating method called the Nuclear Ensemble Approach (NEA), has revolutionized our ability to calculate these interactions efficiently. This method bridges the gap between complex quantum mechanical calculations and practical spectroscopy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-the-nuclear-ensemble-approach&quot;&gt;What is the Nuclear Ensemble Approach?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine trying to predict how a molecule will absorb light. The traditional quantum mechanical way would require solving the Schrödinger equation for both ground and excited states, considering all possible vibrational and electronic states - an extremely complex task! The Nuclear Ensemble Approach offers a clever shortcut that gives us surprisingly accurate results by sampling the ground state wavefunction and using these samples to predict the photoabsorption spectra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-quantum-mechanical-foundation&quot;&gt;The Quantum Mechanical Foundation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its core, NEA is based on the reflection principle from quantum mechanics. Instead of calculating the full quantum mechanical problem, we:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sample the ground state quantum wavefunction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Calculate vertical excitations for each sample&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Combine these excitations into a spectrum&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach cleverly avoids calculating the excited state wavefunction, which is typically the most computationally expensive part of traditional methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In plain English:&lt;/strong&gt; We’re calculating how likely the molecule is to absorb light at different energies, taking into account how the molecule’s structure affects its interaction with light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;applications&quot;&gt;Applications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presented method stands as a reliable and relatively cheap way of predicting photoabsorption cross-sections of Volatile Organic Compounds, making it extremely attractive to Atmospheric Chemists. As the calculation of photoabsorption cross-sections plays a crutial role in the evaluation of photolysis rate of such molecules in the atmosphere, and they are extremely difficult to deteremine empiricaly, the use of insilico methods is becoming more and more viable. To further drive this, optimal sampling has been proposed by Stepan Srsen, whereby a reduction of the sample is performed to improve the efficiency of the overall calculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;practicality-vs-precision&quot;&gt;Practicality vs. Precision&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the NEA might not provide the extremely fine details that more complex quantum mechanical methods offer, this trade-off is often exactly what atmospheric chemists need. In studying atmospheric processes, we’re typically more interested in the overall shape and intensity of absorption bands rather than their precise vibronic structure. 
The NEA’s ability to efficiently calculate photoabsorption cross-sections for unstable VOCs has made it an invaluable tool in atmospheric chemistry. When combined with optimal sampling techniques, it provides a practical pathway for studying these elusive molecules that are so crucial to our understanding of atmospheric processes, from urban smog formation to global climate chemistry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Takeaway:&lt;/strong&gt; The Nuclear Ensemble Approach represents a significant breakthrough in computational photochemistry, offering atmospheric scientists a practical tool for studying light-molecule interactions that were previously either computationally intractable or experimentally challenging to measure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;t60&quot;&gt;Other Blog posts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;side-nav&quot;&gt;

  

    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/identifying-functional-groups&quot;&gt;Computational Chemistry &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;Identifying molecular functional groups&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/nuclear-ensemble-approach&quot;&gt;Photochemistry &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;The Nuclear Ensemble Approach&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/what-is-atmospec&quot;&gt;Atmospheric Chemistry &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;AtmoSpec: A Revolutionary Tool for Atmospheric Chemists&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/predicting-solubility&quot;&gt;Computational Chemistry &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;Predicting molecular properties: Solubility&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li class=&quot;text-right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/archive/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More ›&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;


  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>

			
				<category term="blog" />
			
			
				<category term="Nuclear Ensemble Approach" />
			
				<category term="NEA" />
			
				<category term="photoabsorption cross-sections" />
			
				<category term="Quantum Chemistry" />
			
				<category term="Atmospec" />
			
				<category term="Python" />
			

			<published>2024-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>http://localhost:4000/blog/what-is-atmospec</id>
			<title>AtmoSpec: A Revolutionary Tool for Atmospheric Chemists</title>
			<link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/what-is-atmospec" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AtmoSpec: A Revolutionary Tool for Atmospheric Chemists" />
			<updated>2024-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Konstantin N</name>
					
					
						<email>kon50@hotmail.co.uk</email>
					
					
						<uri>http://k-nom.com</uri>
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>UV/Vis Spectroscopy for all!</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/what-is-atmospec">&lt;p&gt;In the realm of atmospheric chemistry, &lt;strong&gt;Volatile Organic Compounds (VOCs)&lt;/strong&gt; are extremely important, as they can significantly influence air quality and climate, yet their photochemical reactivities and lifetimes are often poorly understood. This lack of knowledge is primarily due to the challenges associated with isolating and measuring these transient VOCs, which stands in the way of conventional laboratory methods. 
Understanding how VOCs interact with sunlight is essential for developing accurate atmospheric chemistry models. &lt;strong&gt;Photoabsorption cross-sections&lt;/strong&gt; are key parameters that describe how much light a molecule can absorb at different wavelengths. This information is crucial for predicting the photolysis processes that VOCs undergo, which in turn affects their reactivity and lifetime in the atmosphere. Unfortunately, obtaining these cross-sections experimentally can be difficult, often unfeasable due to their instability. Recent advances in computational photochemistry allow for the calculation of these photoabsorption cross-sections, but this can be inaccessible to those less computationally savvy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;atmospec-an-automated-workflow-using-nea&quot;&gt;AtmoSpec: An Automated Workflow Using NEA&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To address these challenges, the InSilico Photochemistry group at the University of Bristol have developed an interactive computational tool, AtmoSpec, that automates the calculation of photoabsorption cross-sections for VOCs using the &lt;strong&gt;Nuclear Ensemble Approach (NEA)&lt;/strong&gt;. This automated workflow simplifies the process, allowing users to input a molecule’s structure via a simple SMILES code and select a theoretical framework. AtmoSpec then performs the necessary quantum chemistry calculations using ORCA, and provides users with the photoabsorption cross-section for the molecule’s low-energy conformers, along with estimates of photolysis rate coefficients for various actinic fluxes. This abstraction of a complex computational process makes advances in computational chemistry accessible to researchers less familiar with such methods, giving them access to quantum mechanical tools in their respective areas of research&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AtmoSpec is built on the Aiidalab ecosystem, with an integrated database and workflow manager for seamless execution of calculations and storage of results. Moreover, Quantum Chemistry calculations can be configured for local execution or on the cloud, allowing for greater flexibility. Similarly, the web application delivery allows for remote access from anywhere in the world, and the containerization via Docker ensures robust deployment in any environment. The open source nature encourages contributions and collaborations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;future-improvements&quot;&gt;Future Improvements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking ahead, the InSilicoPhotochemistry group are committed to continuous improvement of the tool. Future enhancements will focus on implementing a improvements in the Nuclear Ensemble Approach, such as &lt;a href=&quot;/portfolio/rep-sampling-for-nea/&quot; title=&quot;Learn about representative sampling techniques&quot;&gt;Representative Sampling Techniques&lt;/a&gt; to improve the efficiency of the algorithm, thereby making it more applicable to larger, more complex molecules. Additionally, interfacing the application with the GPU accellerated package TeraChem will provide appreciable speed up in the quantum chemistry calculations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AtmoSpec is poised to revolutionize the study of VOCs in atmospheric chemistry by providing an accessible and automated method for calculating photoabsorption cross-sections. It empowers researchers to gain deeper insights into the impact of these compounds on our environment without the need for costly laboratory experiments, and in a timely fashion. Whether you are a seasoned scientist or a newcomer to the field, AtmoSpec is a valuable resource that can enhance your understanding of a molecule’s photochemical properties. Additionally, with the planned improvements, its efficiency is set to increase dramatically resulting in wider applicability to more complex molecules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information and to access AtmoSpec, visit the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ispg-group/aiidalab-ispg&quot;&gt;ATMOSPEC GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;t60&quot;&gt;Other Blog posts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;side-nav&quot;&gt;

  

    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/identifying-functional-groups&quot;&gt;Computational Chemistry &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;Identifying molecular functional groups&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/nuclear-ensemble-approach&quot;&gt;Photochemistry &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;The Nuclear Ensemble Approach&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/what-is-atmospec&quot;&gt;Atmospheric Chemistry &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;AtmoSpec: A Revolutionary Tool for Atmospheric Chemists&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/predicting-solubility&quot;&gt;Computational Chemistry &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;Predicting molecular properties: Solubility&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li class=&quot;text-right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/archive/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More ›&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;


  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>

			
				<category term="blog" />
			
			
				<category term="Atmospec" />
			
				<category term="Atmospheric Chemistry" />
			
				<category term="Quantum Chemistry" />
			
				<category term="Open source" />
			
				<category term="Software" />
			
				<category term="Python" />
			

			<published>2024-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>http://localhost:4000/blog/predicting-solubility</id>
			<title>Predicting molecular properties: Solubility</title>
			<link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/predicting-solubility" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Predicting molecular properties: Solubility" />
			<updated>2024-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Konstantin N</name>
					
					
						<email>kon50@hotmail.co.uk</email>
					
					
						<uri>http://k-nom.com</uri>
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>Save the tedious lab work!</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/predicting-solubility">&lt;p&gt;In the realms of pharmaceuticals and agrochemicals, solubility is a cornerstone of efficacy and safety. It is defined as the amount of a substance that will dissolve in a given volume of solvent. relating to both
the solute and the solvent, as well as the temperature and pressure. Solubility  is commonly expressed in terms
of intrinsic solubility, where the solubility of a buffered solution is taken at a given temperature and
pressure. The intrinsic solubility of a substrate reflects its inherent ability to dissolve in a specific solvent,
acting as a straightforward representation of a molecule&apos;s likelihood to dissolve. The intrinsic solubility of
a compound at a given pH level is denoted by logS pH and can be derived from the Henderson-Hasselbalch
equation
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset=&quot;UTF-8&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;meta name=&quot;viewport&quot; content=&quot;width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Math Equation&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;script src=&quot;https://polyfill.io/v3/polyfill.min.js?features=es6&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script id=&quot;MathJax-script&quot; async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/npm/mathjax@3/es5/tex-mml-chtml.js&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        $$ \log S_{pH} = \log S_{0} + \log \left( 1 + \alpha \right) $$
        $$ \text{where} \ \alpha = \frac{\sum \alpha_{cA_i}}{\sum \alpha_{nA_j}} $$
    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this form, \(\alpha_{cA_i}\) is the distribution percentage of the i-th charged microspecies while \(\alpha_{nA_j}\) is the
distribution percentage of the j-th neutral microspecies at a given pH. This equation can be used to
determine the pH-dependent solubility curves and the intrinsic solubility making it vital for
understanding the behavior of a given compound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;why-solubility-matters&quot;&gt;Why Solubility Matters&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Solubility is extremely important, for example in the pharmaceutical industry, the aqueous solubility of a
potential drug has a high impact on the progression of a target molecule. High aqueous solubility is
essential to produce drug compounds with the potential to enter the bloodstream circulation so that it
can have an active effect where needed. The aqueous solubility can be a limiting factor in the
progression of a compound, not only due to its impact on the bioavailability, but also due to problems
with the toxicity of poorly soluble molecules, with consequences such as crystallization in the body. In
fact, a lack of efficacy is the major problem encountered with the formulation and development of new
drug compounds, together with pharmacokinetics it accounts for over 50 % of failed development
projects. Similarly, solubility is a vital consideration in the development of agrochemicals, impacting their
environmental and toxicological properties. The accurate prediction of solubility allows for more rapid
development of more robust and effective target compounds. Moreover, it decreases the probability ofan ineffective target making it past the screening stage, thereby allowing for the allocation of more resources to more promising candidates.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;benefits-of-ml-in-solubility-prediction&quot;&gt;Benefits of ML in Solubility Prediction:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The demand for new drug-like compounds is ever-growing, motivated by the exponentially increasing
population size as well as the constant emergence of new diseases and viruses. As such, the empirical
techniques used to predict solubility become less and less suitable for the mammoth task of rapidly
screening lead compounds due to the sheer number that could be considered. New techniques are required for the prediction of solubility, that are
robust and accurate to help minimize the cost of drug development as well as reduce the wastage of
resources. The advent of machine learning, coupled with developments in computational chemistry
provide a natural progression to the in-silico simulation of molecular properties such as solubility. By utilizing models such as Graph Convolutional Networks (GCNs) and Random Forests, researchers can predict solubility based on molecular structure and other relevant features, providing valuable insights early in the development pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;t60&quot;&gt;Other Blog posts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;side-nav&quot;&gt;

  

    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/identifying-functional-groups&quot;&gt;Computational Chemistry &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;Identifying molecular functional groups&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/nuclear-ensemble-approach&quot;&gt;Photochemistry &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;The Nuclear Ensemble Approach&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/what-is-atmospec&quot;&gt;Atmospheric Chemistry &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;AtmoSpec: A Revolutionary Tool for Atmospheric Chemists&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/predicting-solubility&quot;&gt;Computational Chemistry &amp;middot; &lt;strong&gt;Predicting molecular properties: Solubility&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    
      &lt;li class=&quot;text-right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/blog/archive/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More ›&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;


  
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>

			
				<category term="blog" />
			
			
				<category term="Solubility" />
			
				<category term="Computational Chemistry" />
			
				<category term="QSAR" />
			
				<category term="Machine Learning" />
			
				<category term="Graph Convolutional Networks" />
			
				<category term="Python" />
			

			<published>2024-09-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/rep-sampling-for-nea/thesis-report/</id>
			<title>Representative sampling in the Nuclear Ensemble Approach - full report</title>
			<link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/rep-sampling-for-nea/thesis-report/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Representative sampling in the Nuclear Ensemble Approach - full report" />
			<updated>2024-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Konstantin N</name>
					
					
						<email>kon50@hotmail.co.uk</email>
					
					
						<uri>http://k-nom.com</uri>
					
				</author>
			
			<summary></summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/rep-sampling-for-nea/thesis-report/">&lt;embed src=&quot;/assets/thesis_report.pdf&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;600px&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf&quot; /&gt;

</content>

			
				<category term="reports" />
			
			
				<category term="numpy" />
			
				<category term="EDA" />
			
				<category term="pandas" />
			
				<category term="matplotlib" />
			
				<category term="python" />
			

			<published>2024-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/biscuit-dunking-analysis/biscuit-report/</id>
			<title>Biscuit dunking analysis report</title>
			<link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/biscuit-dunking-analysis/biscuit-report/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Biscuit dunking analysis report" />
			<updated>2024-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Konstantin N</name>
					
					
						<email>kon50@hotmail.co.uk</email>
					
					
						<uri>http://k-nom.com</uri>
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>A deep learning data mining project.</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/biscuit-dunking-analysis/biscuit-report/">&lt;embed src=&quot;/assets/biscuit_report.pdf&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;600px&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf&quot; /&gt;

</content>

			
				<category term="reports" />
			
			
				<category term="numpy" />
			
				<category term="EDA" />
			
				<category term="pandas" />
			
				<category term="matplotlib" />
			
				<category term="python" />
			

			<published>2024-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/atmospec-data-visualization-module/atmospec-report/</id>
			<title>Atmospec data visualization module report</title>
			<link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/atmospec-data-visualization-module/atmospec-report/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Atmospec data visualization module report" />
			<updated>2024-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Konstantin N</name>
					
					
						<email>kon50@hotmail.co.uk</email>
					
					
						<uri>http://k-nom.com</uri>
					
				</author>
			
			<summary></summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/atmospec-data-visualization-module/atmospec-report/">&lt;embed src=&quot;/assets/atmospec_report.pdf&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;600px&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf&quot; /&gt;

</content>

			
				<category term="reports" />
			
			
				<category term="HTML" />
			
				<category term="CSS" />
			
				<category term="Jekyll" />
			
				<category term="Markdown" />
			

			<published>2024-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/cloud-paradigm-atlas-data-processing/atlas-report/</id>
			<title>ATLAS data processing report</title>
			<link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/cloud-paradigm-atlas-data-processing/atlas-report/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ATLAS data processing report" />
			<updated>2024-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Konstantin N</name>
					
					
						<email>kon50@hotmail.co.uk</email>
					
					
						<uri>http://k-nom.com</uri>
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>A demonstration of scalability potential using cloud technologies</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/cloud-paradigm-atlas-data-processing/atlas-report/">&lt;embed src=&quot;/assets/atlas_report.pdf&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;600px&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf&quot; /&gt;

</content>

			
				<category term="reports" />
			
			
				<category term="HTML" />
			
				<category term="CSS" />
			
				<category term="Jekyll" />
			
				<category term="Markdown" />
			

			<published>2024-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>http://localhost:4000/guides/web-building/</id>
			<title>Web Building Homepage</title>
			<link href="http://localhost:4000/guides/web-building/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Web Building Homepage" />
			<updated>2024-08-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Konstantin N</name>
					
					
						<email>kon50@hotmail.co.uk</email>
					
					
						<uri>http://k-nom.com</uri>
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>web design and implementation... </summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/guides/web-building/">&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;medium-4 medium-push-8 columns&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;panel radius&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p id=&quot;toc&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul id=&quot;markdown-toc&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#coming-soon&quot; id=&quot;markdown-toc-coming-soon&quot;&gt;Coming Soon!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- /.medium-4.columns --&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;medium-8 medium-pull-4 columns&quot;&gt;

    &lt;h2 id=&quot;coming-soon&quot;&gt;Coming Soon!&lt;/h2&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</content>

			
				<category term="guides" />
			
				<category term="python" />
			
			

			<published>2024-08-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		</entry>
	
</feed>